<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christ exalted: in a sermon begun to be preached at Debenham in Suffolk, upon the 14. day of Febr. last, upon Coloss. 3. 11. / By Hanserd Knollys. Who was stoned out of the pulpit (as he was preaching) by a company of rude fellowes, and poor women of that town; who were sent for, called together, and set on by a malignant high-constable, who lives in the same town. Also, another sermon, preached at Stradbrooke in Suffolk, the 13. day of Febr. last, concerning sanctification; upon Ephes. 1. 4.</title>
            <author>Knollys, Hanserd, 1599?-1691.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87817</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing K706</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E284_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200061</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860865</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860865</idno>
            <idno type="VID">158497</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87817)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158497)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 47:E284[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christ exalted: in a sermon begun to be preached at Debenham in Suffolk, upon the 14. day of Febr. last, upon Coloss. 3. 11. / By Hanserd Knollys. Who was stoned out of the pulpit (as he was preaching) by a company of rude fellowes, and poor women of that town; who were sent for, called together, and set on by a malignant high-constable, who lives in the same town. Also, another sermon, preached at Stradbrooke in Suffolk, the 13. day of Febr. last, concerning sanctification; upon Ephes. 1. 4.</title>
                  <author>Knollys, Hanserd, 1599?-1691.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May 16th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Colossians III, 11 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158497:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Chriſt Exalted: IN A SERMON Begun to be preached at <hi>Debenham</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> upon the 14. day of <hi>Febr.</hi> laſt, upon <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.11.</p>
            <p>By HANSERD KNOLLYS.</p>
            <p>Who was ſtoned out of the Pulpit (as he was Preaching) by a company of rude fellowes, and poor women of that Town; who were ſent for, called together, and ſet on by a Malignant High-Conſtable, who lives in the ſame Town.</p>
            <p>ALSO, ANOTHER SERMON Preached at <hi>Stradbrooke</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> the 13. day of Febr. laſt, concerning Sanctification; upon Epheſ. 1.4.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>GALAT 4.16.</hi>
               </bibl> Am I therefore become your enemy, becauſe I tell you the truth.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HEBR. 12.14.</hi>
               </bibl> Follow Peace with all men, and holineſſe, without which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 CORINTH. 11.25.</hi>
               </bibl> Once was I ſtoned.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JOHN 10.32.</hi>
               </bibl> For which of theſe good works do you ſtone me?</q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the Year, 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:158497:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE <hi>Committee of Examinations;</hi> Grace and Peace from God, through CHRIST.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>HONOVRABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IT may be judged an act of great boldneſſe in me, who am under the Examination of this Honourable Committee, to dedicate my poor labours at <hi>Debenham</hi> and <hi>Stradbrook,</hi> to your patronage; eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to publiſh them to the world: Had not the hard reports of ſome perſons (too much credited by many) conſtrained me to vindicate firſt the truth, and in the next place to give ſome ſatisfaction to many, who have heard thoſe reports, I ſhould not have been ſo bold; the conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of mine own inability, and the knowledge of the profitable labours of many both learned and godly, hath to this time, and ſtill had juſtly hindred me from publiſhing any thing by print to the view of the World: Wherefore I (being thus inforced to print my Sermons) pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them to your Honours; wherein you have the ſumme and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of all that I preached in <hi>Suffolk</hi> (as many witneſſes can teſtifie.) For my main endeavours there was, to exalt Christ, and to preſſe my Hearers to Sanctification in heart and life. And if the Lord ſhall pleaſe to make my poor labours a bleſſing to any, he will get glory, and I have my reward with him. Howſoever, I humbly ſubmit both my ſelf and my Book, to the Examination and determination of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Committee.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours to ſerve you in the Lord, HANSERD KNOLLYS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158497:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>COLLOS. 3.11.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Chriſt is all, and in all.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> who was a choſen veſſell unto the Lord, to beare his name before the Gentiles, Acts 9 15. wrote this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to the Saints, and Faithfull brethren in Chriſt, which were at Coloſſe, chap. 1. verſe 2. And as the Enſigne-bearer of His glorious Name diſplayed the Magnificency, and tranſcendent Excellencie of Chriſt, in the words of the Text, <hi>Chriſt is all, and in all.</hi> And that he might lift up Chriſts All-ſufficiencie, he nullifies all other excellencies whatſoever, chap. 3. ver. 11 Where he gives the Coloſſians to underſtand, that the advantage of a Jew above a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, the dignity of a Scythian, above a Barbarian, or the Immunities of a Freeman above a Bondſlave, however eſteemed amongſt men, are nothing without <hi>Chriſt, who is all, and in all;</hi> Theſe words have their dependance upon the exhortation unto Mortification, chap. 3. verſ. 5. Which exhortation the Apoſtle preſſed upon the Coloſſians, by telling them, verſ. 9.10. they had put off the Old-Man with his deeds, &amp; had put on the New-Man, &amp;c. Where (that is) in which State of Regeneration, there is neither Greek, nor Jew, &amp;c. But <hi>Chriſt is all, and in all.</hi> The leſſon to be learned hence is this, to wit, <hi>Chriſt is all, and in all, in the New-Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> Two thighs needs ſome explanation in this Doctrine, <hi>viz.</hi> 1. Who is here meant by the New-Man? and ſecondly, How <hi>Chriſt is all, and in all,</hi> in the New-Man? By the New-Man, here, we are to underſtand (as was intended by the Apoſtle) a true beleever, or a faithfull Brother in Chriſt, one ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called a Saint, who is redeemed in the Spirit of his minde, and hath put on the New-Man, Epheſ. 4 23, 24. which is done, when by the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty operation of the holy Spirit, in the Promiſes given unto us, we are made partakers of the Divine nature, 2 Pet. 1.3, 4. <hi>Non per parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipationem Eſſentiae, ſed per communicationem Spiritus, &amp; gratiae ejus.</hi> Gal. 4 6. Epheſ. 4.6. thus being by the Spirit and Faith united with Chriſt, we are made a new creature, or creation. 2 Cor. 5.17. have a new Heart, Ezek. 36.26, 27. and walke in newneſſe of life, Rom. 6.4. And ſuch may be ſaid to have put on the New-Man,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:158497:3"/>the ſum then is this, <hi>Chriſt is all, and in all,</hi> in every true Beleever in every Juſtified-Sanctified perſon, wo hath a New-heart, and walke in newneſſe of life. Touching the Second particular, to wit, How <hi>Chriſt is all, and in all,</hi> in the new man? The Lord Jeſus Chriſt, (who is all in himſelfe, for in him dwelleth all the Fulneſſe of the Godhead bodily, Col. 2.9. which was the pleaſure of God, that in all things he might have the preheminence, Col. 1.18, 19.) <hi>is all, and in all,</hi> in the New-Man. Firſt, Fundamentally, I mean Chriſt is the Foundation of all, 1 Cor. 3.11. For other Foundation can no man lay then that is laid, which is Ieſus Chiriſt; I ſay Chriſt is the Foundation of all that Faith, Repentance, Love, &amp; other gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, gifts, and fruits of the Spirit, which are in every true beleever: He is a living fountain full of grace, and from his fulneſſe have we all received grace for grace, Joh. 1.14, 16. Secondly, Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catively, I meane, Chirſt doth communicate all unto the New-Man, to wit, Life, Light, Grace, and Glory, &amp;c. We have nothing, but what we have received, and we have received all from his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Epheſ. 4.7. Joh. 1.16. The Titles given to Chriſt in the Scripture of truth, will make this appear yet more fully, <hi>viz.</hi> That Chriſt is all in the New-Man, or in every true Beleever: I ſhall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſome.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt is our life, Col. 3.4. Chriſt is the life of a Beleever, even eternall Life, 1 Joh. 5.11, 12. That is to ſay, The everlaſting Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all well-being of a beleever, is by union and communion with Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, in whom he lives a life of grace here, and with whom he ſhall live a life of glory hereafter. Yea all thoſe ſpirituall breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of the hunger-thirſting ſoule after the enjoyment of God in any of his holy Ordinances, are from Chriſt, and from him are all thoſe quicknings, and all that life we have in Prayer, Preaching, Conference, and other ſpirituall duties. In a word, the ſpirit of life himſelfe, who ſo ſweetly refreſheth the weary ſoule, comforts the ſorrowfull heart, and quickens the ſanctified affections, is from Chriſt, and he is called the Spirit of the Son, Gal. 4.6. whom God ſends forth into the hearts of his Children.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Chriſt is the true light of every beleever, or in the New-Man; That was the true Light, Joh. 1.9. even Jeſus Chriſt, who inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the eyes of our vnderſtanding, that we may know what is the hope of his calling, and what the riches of the glory of his inheritance in the Saints, and what is the exceeding greatnes of his power to us-ward, who beleeve, Ephe. 1.17, 18, 19. And though the hearts of men and women be very darke, yet God who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the light to ſhine out of darkneſſe, hath ſhined in our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:158497:3"/>hearts, (who are beleevers) to give the light of the knowledge of the glory of God in the Face of Ieſus Chriſt. 2 Cor. 4.6. And the Apoſtle tells the ſanctified Epheſians, that they were ſometimes darkneſſe, but now ye are light in the Lord, Epheſ. 5.8. And indeed, all that heavenly knowledge, and ſpirituall underſtanding, which beleevers have in the myſterie of the Goſpel, they had it from Chriſt; In whom are are hid all the treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge, Col. 2.2, 3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Chriſt is the Bread of life to beleevers, Joh. 6.35, 48, 51. He is the Spirituall meat and drink of their ſouls, who beleeve in him, they that eat him ſhall live by him, Joh. 6.55, 57. All that Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all nouriſhment, and ſoul refreſhment, which beleevers have in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, duties, Ordinances, &amp;c. is from Chriſt, whoſe fleſh is meate indeed, and his blood is drinke indeed, communicated by his holy ſpirit unto his people in thoſe promiſes, duties, Ordinances, &amp;c. Chriſt is Milke and wine, to be had without money, Iſa. 55.1. that will quench the thirſt of the new-borne babes in Chriſt, which ſo much deſire the ſincere milke of the worde, that they may grow thereby, 1 Pet. 2.2, 3. and that will make the mournfull ſpirit of a a doubting or back-ſliding Beleever, to have a cheerefull counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, when his broken heart is cheered and warmed, yea melted, and comforted with the blood of Chriſt his Redeemer. Chriſt is Water of life, a pure River of living Water cleere as Cryſtall, flowes from this Fountain in the hearts of Beleevers, Rev 22.1, 17. Joh. 7.37, 38. &amp; Ioh. 4.10.13, 14. This will ſatisfie the thirſty ſoul, as Chiriſt Promiſed Mat. 5.6, 11, therfore hee cried, If any man thirſt, let him come to me and drinke. Chriſt is the the tree of life, which beareth twelve manner of fruits, and yeeldeth her fruit every moneth, whoſe leaves are for the healing of the Nations. Revel. 22.2. Chriſt is ſaid to make a feaſt of wine and fat things full of Marrow, Iſa. 25.6. and he thus ſpeakes to beleevers, eate, O Friends, drinke, yea drinke, abundantly, O beloved, Cant. 5.1. I might be exceeding large in particularizing many other his Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, as namely; Chriſt is a beleevers Juſtification, Sanctification, Redemption, 1 Cor. 1.30. He is alſo our Peace, Epheſ. 2.14. our Righteouſneſſe, Ier. 23.6. Our Advocate with the Father. 1 Iohn 2.1, 2. Our King, High-Prieſt, and Prophet, Our Father, Husband, Brother, our All. Thus it may appear, that Chriſt is all in the New-Man. How is Chriſt all, in all in the New-Man? I conceive, It is ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by way of Preheminence, as it is expreſſed, Col. 1.18, 19. That is, In all, which is in the New-Man, or in a Beleever Chriſt ought to have the preheminence; Firſt, as hee is the Author thereof,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:158497:4"/>for inſtance, That precious faith of Gods Elect, which is in the New-Man is an excellent grace, but yet Chriſt muſt have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence above that faith, becauſe he is the Author of it, Heb. 12.2. And ſo above all other graces, gifts, and fruits of the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as he is the preſerver of all in the New-Man, every beleever, is called and Sanctified by God the Father, and preſerved in Jeſus Chriſt, Iude 1. And the Beleever is not onely preſerved in the ſtate of Grace by Chriſt, but the Grace of God wrought in him, to wit, faith, &amp;c. Is by Chriſt preſerved alſo; namely, by the Interceſſion of Chriſt. I have prayed for thee, that thy faith fail not.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as he is the finiſher, who ſtrengtheneth, ſtabliſheth, and perfecteth all in the New-Man. Chriſt is not onely the Author, but the Finiſher of our Faith. Heb. 12.2. He is the <hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega;</hi> the beginning and the ending of all thoſe Graces, gifts, and fruits of the Spirit, which are in the New-Man. Revel. 1 8. Thus <hi>Chriſt is all, and in all, in the New-Man.</hi> He is the Author, Preſerver, and finiſher of all. He purchaſed all, He is the Donour of all, He is the Beauty of all, the Summe of all, the Perfection of all, in the New-Man.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
               </label> This was the good pleaſure of the Fathers will, that all fulneſſe, all-ſufficiencie, all ſpiritualneſſe ſhould dwell in Chriſt, and ſhould by Chriſt be communicated to his people, that in all things Chriſt might have the preheminence, Col. 1.18, 19. And thus God will have it done to the Man Chriſt Jeſus, whom he delighted to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, for the ſervice Chriſt did unto his Father in the Redemption of his people, therefore he gave him a Name, above every Name, <hi>Chriſt is all, and in all.</hi> Which honour &amp; dignity, Chriſt will at the laſt day proſtrate at the feet of his Father, that God may be <hi>all in all.</hi> 1 Cor. 15.28. Moreover, this being the deſigne of God, that Chriſt ſhould communicate all grace, gifts, &amp;c. unto his people. It was requiſite, that all fulneſſe ſhould be in Chriſt, and ſo we read, John. 1.14, 16. Yea the great neceſſitie of the Lords redeemed ones, to have a conſtant ſupplie of grace, and ſpirituall gifts, alſo a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuall growth of the fruits of the ſpirit, requires this all-fulneſſe to be in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> Seeing, <hi>Chriſt is all, and in all,</hi> in the New-Man; Let us hence be Inſtructed. Firſt, to prize Chriſt highly, to ſet an high eſteeme upon Chriſt, to let Him have the preheminence, who is <hi>all in all.</hi> It is that which the Prophet complained of, Iſa. 53.3. He, to wit Chriſt, was deſpiſed, and rejected of men, and we eſteemed him not. We are apt to ſlight Chriſt, and to diſeſteem Him, becauſe we diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158497:4"/>not that beauty, excellencie, riches, and glory, which is in Himſelfe, we are ignorant of the worth of Chriſt, and know not our need of him, and therefore we do not ſo prize him, as we ought. Theſe two Conſiderations, I deſire, to propound, as motives, to prize Chriſt. Firſt, Chriſt his worth, which I may hint unto you in three particulars, to wit, 1. The unvaluable preciouſneſſe of his blood, which hath in it a cleanſing vertue, 1 John 1.7, 9. And the blood of Ieſus Chriſt his Son, cleanſed us from all ſin, therefore, we are ſaid, to be juſtified by his blood, Rom. 5.9. Let me aske you, who now beleeve, How did you eſteem of this precious blood of Chriſt? When you were ſighing-out your mournfull requeſt to God in ſecret corners, for one drop of Chriſts blood, one dram of the grace of God, and faith of God his Elect, one word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, one ſmile of a reconciled Father, or one beam of the light of Gods countenance, did you not prize the blood of Chriſt above all corruptible things, as ſilver, gold, honour, riches, pleaſure, &amp;c. Did you not eſteem the leaſt drop of it more precious, then all creature-comforts whatſoever, as friends, liberties, and life? Again, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious blood of Chriſt hath a purging quality, Heb 9.14 The blood of Chriſt ſhall purge your conſciences from dead workes, to ſerve the living God. Sin doth both contract guiltineſſe, and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and therefore the blood of Chriſt doth both cleanſe, and purge, pardon, and purifie, therefore we are alſo ſaid, to be ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the blood of Chriſt; Heb. 13.12. Wherefore Jeſus alſo, that he might ſanctifie the people with his own blood; Suffered with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the gate. Oh beloved, what can be eſteemed ſo precious to a gracious heart, as this blood of Chriſt, which waſheth away all thoſe defilements, and uncleanneſſes, which through our corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions cleave unto us, even in our beſt actions, and holy duties: Such of you, (as have many a time groaned in prayer to God under the feeling ſence and ſight of any corruption) know by experience, what high eſteem you have had of the blood of Chriſt to ſave you, from your uncleanneſſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the unſearchable riches of his grace. Epheſ. 3.8. To me who am leſſe then the leaſt of all Saints, is this grace given, that I ſhould preach among the Gentiles, the unſearchable riches of Chriſt. Chriſts riches are of ſuch an hight, depth, length, and bredth, that paſſeth knowledge, yea thus much is ſpoken of the love of Chriſt. Epheſ. 3.18, 19. Alſo Faith in Chriſt is called precious faith, 2 Pet. 1.1. To them, that have obtained like precious faith with us, through the Righteouſneſſe of God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, yea all the Graces of Chriſt are the riches of the poore
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158497:5"/>Saints, Jam. 2.5. God hath choſen the poor of the world, rich in grace, &amp;c. Tell me, beloved, how did you eſteem of the riches of Chriſt, when you being poor in ſpirit, mourned for Chriſt and his grace, when you diſcerned Faith, Love, Humility, &amp;c. in others of the children of God, did you not prize it highly in them? Did you not account them happy, rich, and bleſſed, whom Chriſt had inriched with thoſe jewels, and adorned with ſuch graces? Ah how much more ſhould you now prize Chriſt, in whom is all fulneſſe of theſe unſearchable riches, and eſpecially conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that from his fulneſſe you have received grace for grace, Ioh. 1.14, 16.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the glorious liberties of his Spirit; for where the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord is, there is libertie. 2 Cor. 3.17. Not any carnall liberty to ſin, and ſo fulfill the luſts of the Fleſh, Gal. 5.13. but Spirituall liberty, and freedome from ſin. I mean not a perfect and totall freedome from all ſin, as if the people of God could never ſin after Converſion. For if we ſay, that we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us, 1 Joh. 1 8, 10. But I mean a freedome: Firſt, from the guilt of ſin. Rom. 8 33. And the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, Coloſ. 2.13. That he hath forgiven us all treſpaſſes. Secondly, from the polution or filth of ſin, Zach. 13.1. A fountain ſet open to Beleevers for ſin and for uncleaneſſe. And Ezek. 36.25, 29. God promiſed they ſhall be cleane, and he will ſave them from all their uncleanneſſes. Thirdly, from the raigning power of ſin: Rom. 6.14. Sin ſhall not have dominion over you, under grace. Fourthly, from the puniſhment due for ſin, which is the cure of the Law, Gal. 3.13. or condemnation, Rom. 8.1. or any other ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="2">2 The great need you have of Chriſt, may move you to praiſe him, and ſet an high eſteeme of him. Chriſt is the one thing ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, and therefore the Titles given him in the Scripture, are ſuch as declare his uſefullneſſe to Beleevers, for he is our Life, our Light, our Bread, Water, Milke, Wine, His fleſh our meat indeed, His blood our drink indeed; He is our Father, our Husband, our Brother, our Friend, our King, Prieſt, and Prophet; He is our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification, Sanctification, and Redemption; He is our Peace, our All. We can have no acceſſe to God but by his Mediation, no acceptance with God without his Jnterceſſion. Revel. 8.3.4. We cannot reſiſt the next Temptation, neither can we overcome the next Corruption, nor ſhall we be able to ſuffer with patience the next Perſecution, or indure any tribulation, unleſſe we have renewed ſtrength from Chriſt. Beleevers have received, that Grace,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:158497:5"/>they have, from Chriſt, Iohn 1 16. And they cannot have increaſe of grace bu by Chriſt, Iohn 15.1, 2. Lord increaſe our Faith ſaid the Diſciples, neither can they perſevere in grace, unleſſe they be preſerved in Chriſt, Iude 1. To conclude, we are nothing, have nothing, can do nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Chriſt, Iohn 15.5. Without me you can do nothing; that is to ſay, you cannot in your own ſtrength, nor in the ſtrength of any grace recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, do any thing to pleaſe God, or to glorifie God, without me; unleſſe you abide in me, and have renewed ability and ſtrength from me, you can do nothing that God my father will own or crown with acceptance or reward: But yet we who are Believers, have all and abound, Phil. 4.18. can do all things through Chriſt that ſtrengtheneth them, Phil. 4.13. can ſuffer the loſſe of all, Phil. 3.7, 8, 9. yea and conquer all, nay be more then conquerours through Chriſt, Rom. 8.35, 36, 37, 38, 39. Oh conſider your need of Chriſt and learn to prize him, let him be exalted higheſt in your hearts, as the pearl of greateſt worth, as the one thing neceſſary which you moſt of all need, let him be all in all in your communication and converſation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Vſe.</hi> Seeing Chriſt is all and in all in the new-Man, let every one examine whether Chriſt be in him. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Examine your ſelves, know you not that Chriſt is in you, &amp;c. This nearly concernes you belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, for if you have Chriſt, you have all. Chriſt is all you heart but if you loſe him you loſe all; you will loſe your hopes, Comforts, and all your duties, yea you will loſe God, Heaven, and ſoul, and all. It matters not what you have if you want Chriſt, no guifts, duties, reformations, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lifications, or other things whatſoever, will make you happy without Chriſt; And if you enjoy Chriſt, it is not materiall what ever you want, for my God (ſaith the Apoſtle) ſhall ſupply all your need, according to his riches, in glory by Chriſt Jeſus Phil. 4.19. Therfore make ſure that Chriſt is yours. Some would ask this queſtion, How ſhall I ſo examine, that I may know aſſuredly that I have Chriſt? I anſwer, you muſt bring your hearts to the touchſtone of the Word of God, and caſt them into the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance of the Sanctuarie and weigh them there. And to this purpoſe, I ſhall propound one Scripture of truth for your examination and triall, to wit, 2 Cor. 5.17. If any man be in Chriſt he is a new-creature, or creation; That is to ſay, he is new-born, born again, or born of God, Joh. 1.12, 13. But as many as received him, &amp;c. which were born of God. And our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour urged the neceſſitie of this new-birth, Joh. 3.3.5.7, 8. Except a man be born again he cannot ſee the Kingdome of God, he cannot enter into the Kingdome of God, verſ. 5. Now every one who is a new creature in Chriſt, all things are become new in him, or all things are made new [as in the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ecce nova facta ſunt omnia.</hi>] To wit; firſt he is made a new man, Epheſ. 4.21.22.23.24. Col. 3.10.11,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:158497:6"/>and have put on the new-man where Chriſt is all and in all. Secondly, he hath a new heart, Ezek. 36.26. A new heart alſo will I give you, &amp;c. That is, a new will and new affections, yea and a new ſpirit will I put within you, verſe 26. That is (Epheſ. 4.23.) to be renewed in the ſpirit of our minde, to wit, a new judgement or ſpirituall underſtanding in the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Gods will, Col. 1.9. Thirdly, he walkes in newneſſe of life: Rom. 6.4. Even ſo we alſo ſhould walk in newneſſe of life. That is, the converſation of a new-creature ſhould be ſuch as becomes the Goſpell: Phil. 1.27. To wit, humble, harmleſſe, and holy: 1 Pet. 1.15 16. And thus God hath promiſed in the everlaſting covenant of grace, that all and every one of his people ſhall walk: Ezek. 36.27. And I will put my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within you, and cauſe you to walk in my ſtatutes, &amp;c. Examine your ſelves, Are you a new creature? Such of you as have not put off the old man, but ſtill have your old hearts, and your old ſinnes, and walk in your old wayes, and fulfill the old luſts of your ſinfull natures, are not in a new creature, you are not in Chriſt, nor Chriſt in you.</p>
            <p>But ſome may thus ſay within themſelves, I hope my ſoul is in a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter condition, I am not ſo wicked and carnall as ſome others are, neither am I ſo vilde a ſinner as I have been formerly; but I am ſomewhat refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and have forſaken my ſinfull courſes, and begin to delight to hear Sermons, and I pray with my family. To this I would anſwer, although your condition be not ſo deſperate as others, who have lived long under ordinatie meanes of grace, and yet are not at all wrought upon, I muſt tell you, Profeſſors may (through ſtrong Convictions, horrour of conſcience, and feares of Hell) leave the Acts of ſome ſins, and may cuſtomarily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form ſome religious duties, and yet not regenerated. Profeſſors may have leaves like the unfruitfull Figtree, and Lampes like the five fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, they may ſeem to be Religious, and have a forme of Godlineſſe; and not be a New creature, or creation. I might inſtance many ſuch in the Scriptures. <hi>Herod,</hi> Mark. 6.20. He heard <hi>Iohn</hi> gladly, and did many things. <hi>Saul,</hi> 1 Sam. 10.6, 9. was turned into another Man, had another heart, yet unconverted: So thou mayeſt be another Man, and not a New-Man, maieſt have another heart, but not a new heart.</p>
            <p>But I ſpeak not this to adde ſorrow to the afflicted, nor to break the the bruiſed, for though ſome may deceive themſelves herein; Yet ſuch of you as are borne again or borne of God, though but New-borne babes, who have put on the New-Man, have a New heart, and walke in New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life, are in Chriſt, and Chriſt in you.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Vſe.</hi> Seeing, <hi>Chriſt is all, and in all in the New-Man;</hi> Let it ſerve for the conſolation of every true beleeve, Chriſt is yours, and all things are yours: 1 Cor. 3.21, 22, 23. All are yours, and ye are Chriſts, and Chriſt is God. Chriſt is your life, your light, your foode, your All, and by union
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:158497:6"/>with Chriſt, you are one in God, John. 17.21. God is your God and Father, John 20.17. All that is Chriſts is yours, his Wiſdome, Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, Sanctification, Faith, Love, Humility, &amp;c. All in all fulneſſe, was in Him, and dwels in him, for his people, to communicate to them, Epeſ. 4.7. Are you full of ſpirituall wants, you may have ſupply from the fulneſſe of Spiritualls in Chriſt. Doe you want Wiſdome, Faith, love, &amp;c. What ever you want, go to Chriſt for that grace; There is enough in Chriſt to ſatisfie the moſt hunger-thirſting ſoules in ſpirituall things, Epeſ. 1.3. God hath bleſſed us with all ſpirituall bleſſings, in heavenly things in Chriſt; In whom are hid all the treaſures of Wiſdome, and knowledge: Col. 2.3. Doe you want power againſt corruptions? go to Chriſt for ſtrength, His grace is ſufficient for thee, 2 Cor. 12.8.9. There is an all-ſufficiencie in Chriſt, <hi>Chriſt is all,</hi> ſaith the Text, therefore the Apoſtle having Chriſt, ſaid, I have all, I can do all through Chriſt, Phil. 4.13, 18. And know for your further conſolation, that Chiriſt is in all in the New-Man, or in every true Beleever.</p>
            <p>He is in you, Col. 1.2. Chriſt in you, the hope of glory; Chriſt liveth in me ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 Gal. 20. Chriſt is, and lives in a true beleever by participation of his Divine Nature, 2 Pet. 1.3, 4. By incohation of his holy Spirit, Gal. 4.6. and by communication of his ſaving grace, Epheſ. 3.17. and 4 7. Chriſt is in your hearts, in your gifts, in your graces, in your duties, in all, by whom you finde acceptance of your perſons, and ſervices with God your heavenly Father, Epheſ. 1.6. Chriſt is with you, and in you, in all conditions, in all relations, in all Afflictions, Iſa. 63.8 9. And to conclude this uſe, know for your increaſe of joy; that Chriſt, <hi>who is all, and in all in you</hi> will abide in you for ever; Nothing ſhall be able to ſeparate Chriſt and your ſoules, Rom. 8.35, 38, 39. Chriſt is the ſtrength of your heart, and your portion for ever, Pſalm. 73.26.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Vſe.</hi> Seeing <hi>Chriſt is all, and in all in the New-Man,</hi> ſuffer a word of exhortation, which will conſcerne every one preſent to hearken to, <hi>viz.</hi> Both ſuch as are in Chriſt, and out of Chriſt. And I am ſure evere one of you are in one of theſe two eſtates: either you are in Chriſt, or without Chriſt. The firſt branch of the exhortation ſhall be you, who are beleevers, and ſanctified in Chriſt Ieſus, called Saints, ſeeing, Chriſt is all in all, Let him be all in all in your juſtification, take ye heed you bring not any righteouſneſſe of your owne, nor any grace or worke of his in you, to joyne with Chriſt, and his righteouſneſſe in point of juſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Phil. 3.9. This glory Chriſt will not give to another. He is our ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtification, or righteouſneſſe, 1 Cor. 1.30, 31. Chriſt will not permit any coadjutor, concauſe, or cooperator whatſoever in juſtification of ſinners.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:158497:7"/>
            <p>Conſider this you who will not beleeve, unleſſe you could ſee your ſelves ſo holy, ſo humble; except you can firſt have ſuch a ſinne ſubdued, you will not beleeve any of your ſinnes are pardoned, untill you finde and feele in your ſelves a ſoft heart, a broken heart, a praying ſpirit, a mourning ſpirit, you cry out you are not juſtifyed. Oh, ſay you, if I could pray, mourne for ſinne, profit by the meanes, as ſuch and ſuch doe, then I would beleeve: but alas, I have a hard heart, a blinde minde, a perverſe will, carnall affections, &amp;c. I cannot, dare not, I will not beleeve that my ſins are forgiven. Thus moſt profeſſors would bring in (if not their owne righteouſneſſe) ſome grace or work of God in them, to joyne with Chriſt in their juſtification, not conſidering that God juſtifies the ungodly, Rom. 4.5. and that Chriſt is all and in all in the juſtification of ſinners.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let Chriſt be all, in all the gifts of the Spirit, and graces of ſanctification: for, as you heard, he is the Author, the Preſerver, and the finiſher of them all, therefore let him have the preheminence, above all, ſet an high eſteeme of every gift and grace of God, account a little grace better then all the riches, honours, pleaſures, and creature-comforts of this world. But you ought to prize Chriſt farre above all his owne gifts and graces in us, for he is the life of them all, the marrow and ſubſtance of them a I. What is all knowledge, unleſſe ye know God in Chriſt? 1 Cor. 13.2 nothing. What is all Faith, except Chriſt be the object of it? 1 Cor. 13.2 Nothing. Patience, Temperance, and all other Vertues, what are they? but either naturall qualities, or morall habits, unleſſe Chriſt be the root of them; Nature, Education, and acquired gifts of Art may produce the like, yea the ſame, in Heathens. But Chriſt is the luſtre and beauty of each ſpirituall gift and grace: that influence beleevers receive from Chriſt, and thoſe rayes that come from this Sunne of Righteouſneſſe upon their graces, makes them ſhining Saints, beautifull and all glorious within. Heare this you poore in ſpirit, you new-borne babes in Chriſt, who have the perſons of beleevers (eſpecially Preachers) in admiration, and ſet them up on high in your hearts, and extoll them with your tongues, becauſe you diſcerne ſo much humility, love, patience, faith, and other gifts of the Spirit, and graces of ſanctification in them: ſhould you not rather admire Chriſt, exalt Chriſt, and extoll him, who is the purchaſer, the owner, the donor, and the author of all theſe ſpirituall gifts and graces, for we have nothing but what we have received, by his grace we are what we are, and all the grace we have, from his fulneſſe we received it, Joh. 1.16. ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let him receive the glorie of all, and let him have the preheminence in all, for he is all in all.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, let Chriſt be all, in all your affections, words, and actions. Set your affections on Chriſt. Oh let the diſcoveries of that ſuperlative ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie, and glorious beautie of Chriſt, which are made out to your ſoules
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:158497:7"/>by the Spirit and Word of God, draw you to ſet your affections on him, Col. 1.1 2. Love every one, and every thing that God hath put the name of Chriſt upon, for his ſake, but chiefly ſet your affectionate love upon himſelfe, love Chriſt in his Saints, love Chriſt in his meſſengers, in his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, &amp;c. this will quicken your deſires to enjoy more of Chriſt, more of Chriſt in his Saints, Miniſters, Ordinances, and in your owne hearts. On let Chriſt be chiefeſt in your affections, he is altogether love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Cant. 5.16. Let him have your deareſt love, he is the wel-beloved of his Father and yours, 2 Pet. 1.17. let him be your wel-beloved. Chriſt beares you in his armes, everlaſting armes of mercy, yea in his boſome, Iſa. 40.11. &amp; 63.9. Doe you beare him in your heart, and let Chriſt be exalted higheſt there. Againe, let the abſence of Chriſt be the chiefe oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of your ſorrow and mourning, Matth. 9 15. cry after him, enquire for him, give him no reſt untill he returne: this was the practice of the Spouſe, Cant. 3.1, 2, 3, 4. &amp; Cant. 5.4, 6, 8. Oh how was her affections ſet upon her Beloved! tell him I am ſicke of love, Cant. 5.8. Though there be many other juſt occaſions for mourning to the Saints, yet this is the chiefe. If a loving wife cannot thinke of the departure of her deare huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band without ſorrow, how much more ſorrowful will a gracious heart be in the abſence of Chriſt? <hi>Mary</hi> likewiſe who wept, and being asked the reaſon by the Angels, anſwered, <hi>Becauſe they have taken away my Lord, &amp;c.</hi> Joh. 20.11, 13, 15, 16. And as Chriſt ſhould be all in your affections, ſo let him be in your words and actions: ſpeake for him, doe for him, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer for him, let him be the matter of your communications and conferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that you may miniſter grace to the hearers: what ever you do in word or deed, let all be done to the honour of Chriſt, for he that honours the Sonne, honours the Father alſo.</p>
            <p>The other branch of the exhortation, is to ſuch as are in their naturall condition, without Chriſt, ſeeing Chriſt is all &amp; in all, be exhorted to ſeek Chriſt. <hi>Paul</hi> preaching on <hi>Mars</hi>-hill to the Athenians, tells them, God made of one blood all Nations of men, that they ſhould ſeeke the Lord, Act 17.22, 26, 27. and there be many exhortations in holy Scripture to this purpoſe: as Iſa. 55.6, 7. <hi>Seeke ye the Lord while he may be found, &amp;c. Let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and let him returne unto the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> in his ſpeech to <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> Act. 8.20, 21, 22, 23. told him his heart was not right in the ſight of God, that he was <hi>in the gall of bitterneſſe, and in the bond of iniquity.</hi> And yet he exhorted him to repent and pray to God, verſ. 22 Not that any man in his naturall condition can of himſelfe come to Chriſt, deſire him, or ſeeke to enjoy him for none can come to Chriſt except the Father draw him. Joh. 6.44. It is God that workes in us to will and to doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his good pleaſure, Phil. 2.13. So then, ſaith the Apoſtle, it is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:158497:8"/>not of him that willeth, nor of him that runneth, but of God that ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth mercy; onely know this, God requiring poore ſinners to uſe the meanes, he hath appointed, is pleaſed to make that meanes effectuall for their converſion and ſalvation. For if God have purpoſed to ſhew mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and conferre his grace upon your ſoules, he will cauſe you to ſeeke unto him, Ezek. 36.26, 27 37. A new heart will I give you, and I will put my Spirit within you, and cauſe you to walke in my Statutes: Thus ſaith the Lord God, I will yet for this be enquired of by the houſe of Iſrael to doe it for them, verſ. 37. Gods gracious and free promiſes doe not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the meanes he hath appointed to attaine the mercies therein pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed. It pleaſeth him to tye his creatures to the uſe of meanes, when he affords it them, though he will ſometime worke without it. Now the ordinary meanes which God hath in his infinite wiſedome appointed to convert ſinners, and alſo to build them up in Chriſt, is the Word preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Rom. 10.8, 17. This word of the Goſpel God will have preached to every creature in all parts of the world, Mark 16.15. None are exempted or prohibited from hearing the Goſpel preached, but every one that hath an eare is required to heare, Revel. 2.7. And let ſuch as neglect the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the word of God (preached by ſuch as are called and ſent of Chriſt) conſider what the Lord ſaith, Prov. 1. from the 20. verſ. to the 32. verſ. But albeit ſome of you ſee it is that you ought to doe, and that you had need to doe, to wit, to ſeeke the Lord; aſſenting to what you heard in the firſt verſe of the doctrine, that there is much worth, beauty, and excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in Chriſt, and that poore-loſt-undone ſinners ſtand in need of him: Notwithſtanding how to obtaine Chriſt you know not as yet. Let me tell you, God offers you Chriſt upon Goſpel-termes, which are theſe three.</p>
            <p>Firſt, God in the diſpenſation of the Goſpell propounds Chriſt to loſt ſinners, as the onely neceſſary, and all-ſufficient meanes of Salvation: Chriſt is the onely neceſſary means of Salvation, Act. 4.12. Neither is there Salvation in any other. And Chriſt is the All-ſufficient meanes of Salvation, ſo that we need none but him: Heb. 7.25. He is able to ſave them to the umoſt, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God doth offer Chriſt to loſt ſinners without reſpect to price or perſon, He invites them, that have no money, to come, and buy Wine, and milk, (that is to ſay, Chriſt) without price, Iſa 55 1. And any one, that will, are invited to take Chriſt freely: Revel. 22.17 And whoſoever will, let him take the water of life (that is, Chriſt) freely.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God requires, that thoſe, who do receive him, ſhall depart from iniquity, 2. Tim. 2.19. Live ſoberly, righteouſly, and Godly in this preſent world, Ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>us. 2 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. And that they ſhall ſell all, loſe all, and hate all for the ſake of Chriſt, and take up the Croſſe and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:158497:8"/>
            <p>You will ſay to me, Alas, here is my miſerie, to wit, although God propound Chriſt upon good termes to poor ſinners, to me among others, I have no power of my ſelfe to receive Chriſt, to beleeve in him, and accept of him. True, It is not (as I ſaid) in him, that willeth, nor him that runneth, but in God, who ſheweth mercy; Rom. 9.16. It is the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding greatneſſe of his power to us-wards, who beleeve, which muſt be put forth in your hearts, to make you beleeve alſo, according to the working of his mighty power, which he wrought in Chriſt, when he raiſed him from the dead, Epheſ. 1.19, 20. And you ought to wait on God in the diligent uſe of meanes untill the day of his power come upon you, and then you ſhall be a willing, a beleeving people: Pſal. 110.3. I may exhort you to repent of your wickedneſſe, prophaneneſſe, &amp;c. as <hi>Peter</hi> did: Act. 8.22. But God muſt give you repentance unto life, Act. 11.18 It is my duty to preach the Goſpel to you, and to exhort you to ſeek Chriſt. Act. 17.22, 27. but it is the meer mercy and free grace of God to drive you to Chriſt, which nothing but his everlaſting love can move him to doe, Ier. 31.3. You ought to ſeek, and wait, aske, and have, and uſe all the meanes which God hath appointed, and afforded you, both ſecret, private, and publike, Revel. 2.29. But God muſt make the meanes effectuall: Acts 16.14. And therefore I muſt ſay, It is not in me, I cannot draw you to Chriſt, that is the Fathers worke: John 6.44. But having exhorted you to ſeeke him in the uſe of meanes, there I muſt leave you to waite on God for the moving of his holy Spirit, where you muſt lye and continue like the poore impotent man at the poole of Betheſda for healing: And though as he did, ſo you may ſee many a Lame, Blinde, Deaf, Dumb, Naked-leprous ſoule, get healing and goe away rejoycing and praiſing God, and you remaine ſtill ſo impotent, that you cannot get in to the Fountaine, ſet open for ſin and for uncleanneſſe, nor have any that can helpe you in, that you may be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: yet be not diſheartned, as Chriſt came ſuddenly and unexpectedly, and healed the impotent man after long waiting; ſo Chriſt will come ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe to your ſoules that ſeek him, Malac. 3.1. The Lord whom you ſeek ſhall come, ſhall ſuddenly come, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:158497:9"/>
            <head>THE SECOND SERMON.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EPHES 1.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>That we ſhould be holy.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this chapter you have; Firſt, the inſcription of the Epiſtle, verſ. 1. and therein is declared both the Pen-man <hi>Paul;</hi> and his Office, an Apoſtle of of Jeſus Chriſt by the will of God; alſo the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to whom the Epiſtle was written, the Saints, and to the faithfull in Chriſt Jeſus, which are at Epheſus.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A ſalutation, verſ. 2. and therein is expreſſed the matter of the Salutation, <hi>Grace, and Peace;</hi> the perſons ſaluted you, to wit, the Saints; the Author from whom Grace and Peace comes to the Saints: From God our Father, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, A congratulation, verſ. 3. for ſpirituall bleſſings in generall, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> &amp;c. Who hath bleſſed us with all ſpirituall bleſſings &amp;c. or with every ſpirituall bleſſing. Whereof the Apoſtle mentioneth ſome particularly in the following verſes, to wit, Election, Predeſtination, Adoption. In this 4 verſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hints to us.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That there is an Election.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That the Elect are choſen in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That Election was before the World was founded.</p>
            <p>And fourthly, that the Elect of God ſhould be holy, and without blame in his preſence, in love.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the occaſion, and dependence of the words of the Text, which offers to your religious conſideration this plaine Doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> God will have his people to be an holy people. This point of doctrine needeth no explanation; And it is a truth ſo generally aſſented to by all profeſſors, that I ſhall give you but one Scripture, to confirme it. 2 Theſ. 3. <hi>This is the will of God,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> your Sanctification. And
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:158497:9"/>indeed it appeares manifeſtly in the Scripture of truth, that this is Gods holy will.</p>
            <p>Firſt, becauſe God hath choſen them in Chriſt to this end, Epheſ. 1.4. That they ſhould be holy.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God calles his to holineſſe, 1 Theſ. 4.7. God hath not called us to uncleanneſſe, but unto holineſſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God hath given to every one of his the holy ſpirit to ſanctifie them, Rom. 15 16. being ſanctified by the holy ſpirit.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God affords them his holy word, which is a meanes of Sanctification. John. 17.17. Sanctifie them through thy truth, thy word is truth. Yea when they ſin againſt God, he will chaſtiſe them for their profit; that they may be partakers of his holineſſe, Heb. 12.10. So that God would have his people holy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 1. God will have his people to be holy, that he may be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied in juſtifying the ungodly, Rom. 3.26. That he might be juſt, that juſtifieth the ungodly, Rom. 4.5. God juſtifieth the ungodly, that is, He finding men and women in their blood, or in their ſins, Ezek. 16 6, 8. he (in the the time of love) forgives them all their ſins, covers their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe with the skirt of Chriſts Righteouſneſſe, and bids them live; This is done when God enters into covenant with them, and ſo they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come his. Now that God may be juſtified in ſo doing, though he found them ungodly, unbeleevers, impenitent, prophane, &amp;c. He doth not onely forgive them all their ſins, and ſo leave them ungodly, to go on in their wicked waies; But he gives them his holy Spirit of Sanctificaton, who changeth their hearts, renewes the ſpirit of their minde, ſanctifies their wills, and affection, and produceth all thoſe fruits of the ſpirit in them, mentioned, Gal. 5.22, 23. whereby they are made holy in all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of converſation. 1 Pet. 1.15, 16. And this reaſon the Apoſtle gives, Epheſ. 1.4, 6. That we ſhould be holy: to the praiſe of the glory of his grace, and verſe 12. That we ſhould be to the praiſe of his Glory. And herein is God juſtified in juſtifying the ungodly, in that he doth make and keep them holy, Jude 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon</hi> 2. God will have his people to be holy, for the honour and glory of his Son Jeſus Chriſt to whom he hath given them. <hi>All mine are thine</hi> (ſaith Chriſt in his Prayer to his Father, John 17.1, 10.) <hi>and thine are mine, and I am glorified in them,</hi> alſo verſe. 19. <hi>And for their ſakes, I ſanctifie my ſelfe, that they alſo might be ſanctified.</hi> Chriſt ſhall be glorified in his Saints, eſpecially in his Kingly Office, Revel. 15.3, 4. Juſt and true are thy waies; Thou King of Saints; Who ſhall not fear thee, O Lord, and glorifie thy Name, for thou onely art holy. And albeit, now Chriſt, and his poor Saints are ſcorned, and deſpiſed of men; yet that Propheſie of <hi>Enoch,</hi> the ſeventh from <hi>Adam,</hi> will have its accompliſhment, Jude 14.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:158497:10"/>
               <hi>Behold, the Lord commeth with ten thouſand of his Saints. The Lord Ieſus ſhall be revealed from Heaven with his mighty Angels; When he ſhall come to be glorified in his Saints,</hi> 2 Theſ. 17 10. And in that day it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to all the world, that it is the great glory of Jeſus Chriſt, that his Father hath given him ſo many, ten thouſands of Saints to be his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, and himſelfe to be their King, Iſa. 33.17, 22.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſon.</hi> 3. God will have his people holy, that they may enjoy ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall communion with him in this life, and Eternall communion with him in heaven. The Saints do enjoy ſpirituall Communion with God in this life, 1 John 1.3 Truely our fellowſhip is with the father, and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt, and with the Spirit, Phil. 2.1. And they ſhall have eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall communion with God in Heaven, in that Kingdome prepared for them, which then thy ſhall receive, Matth. 25.34. Now this commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with God, none can have without holineſſe. Heb. 12.14. Therefore God will have his people to be holy.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Vſe.</hi> Will God have his people to be holy? Let it be uſefull to us, firſt for enquiry, what holineſſe is? And how God makes His holy? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 1 Theſ. 4 3. 7 Holineſſe or Sanctification is a reall change of the whole Man, from the pollution of ſin, to the purity of the Image of Chriſt Rom. 6.22. But now being made free from ſin, and become ſervants of God, ye have your fruits unto holineſſe Here was a reall change in them from the pollution of ſin, 2 Cor. 3.18. But we all with open face beholding, as in a glaſſe, the glory of the Lord, are changed into the ſame Image. Here was the other part of that reall change in them, to wit, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the purity of the Image of Chriſt. For as men in their naturall eſtate bear the Image of the Earthy firſt-man <hi>Adam;</hi> ſo men in their ſpirituall eſtate bear the Image of the Heavenly ſecond-Man CHRIST, 1 Cor. 15.47, 48, 49. This holineſſe or ſanctification (if you have reſpect to the Author and efficient cauſe thereof) is called the ſanctification of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, 2 Theſ. 2.13. and 1 Pet. 1.2. (If unto the divine act of God) it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Renovation or Renewing of the minde, Epheſ. 4.23, and Rom. 12.2. (If unto the Acts and fruits of holineſſe in beleevers) it is called Faith, love, long ſuffering, gentleneſſe, goodneſſe, meekneſſe, temperance, &amp;c. Gal. 5.22. (If unto the root, fountain, and foundation of holineſſe) the Scripture ſaith; Chriſt is our ſanctification, 1 Cor. 1.30. Thus you hear what holineſſe is. Now God maketh His holy by his Spirit and Word; Whereby he doth convince them, that they are without Chriſt: Epheſ. 2.12. Maketh diſcoverie to them of the worth of Chriſt, their need of him, and Gods offer of him in a covenant of Grace upon Goſpell termes; changing their hearts into the Image of Chriſt, 2 Cor. 3.18. Gives them Faith in Chriſt, Repentance from dead workes, Love to all the Saints, &amp;c. <hi>And ſo the very God of Peace Sanctifie his people,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:158497:10"/>1 Theſſalonians 5.23. Thus much may ſuffice touching the Jnquiry.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Vſe.</hi> Will God have his people to be holy? Let us make uſe of this, to diſcover who are the people of God, &amp; who are not. Thoſe people, that are ungodly, unſanctified, are not the people of God, ſuch may boaſt of their Juſtification, but they deceive themſelves, for God hath no juſtified-unſanctified people, 1 Cor. 6 9, 10, 11. They may talke of the free-grace of God manifeſted to them &amp; bringing them Salvation, but they are delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; for the grace of God, that bringeth Salvation, teacheth us to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ungodlineſſe, and to live godly. Titus. 2.11, 12. Now there are three ſorts of profeſſors, who would be eſteemed the people of God, and yet are not ſanctifyed by the holy ſpirit, they are not holy, and therefore are not the Lords people in Covenant.</p>
            <p>The firſt Sort are all thoſe legall profeſſors, who having been by the ſpirit, and word of God much convinced of ſin, Iohn 16.8. Sorely woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in their conſciences, Proverbes. 18.14. and ſomewhat reformed in their converſations, by hearing godly Preachers, as <hi>Herod</hi> was, Mark 6 20. after all this, goe about to eſtabliſh their own righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and reſt upon their duties, humiliation, and legall reformation; And never have their hearts changed, and renewed, nor Chriſt given of the Father unto them: Theſe are not ſanctified, are not the Lords. Hear what the Apoſtle ſpeakes to ſuch among the Galatians. <hi>Are yee ſo fooliſh? having begun in the Spirit, are you now made perfect by the fleſh? Have you affired ſo many things in vain? If it be yet in vaine.</hi> Well ſuch of you as God hath choſen in Chriſt, that you ſhould bee holy, &amp;c. He will alſo by his Spirit and Word convince you of Righteouſneſſe, to wit, that all your own Righteouſneſſes are as filthy rags, Iſa. 64.6. That being ignorant of Gods Righteouſneſſe, you have gone about to eſtabliſh your owne righteouſneſſe, Rom. 10 3. and that you muſt be found in Chriſt, not having your own righteouſneſſe, which is of the Law; but that which is through the faith of Chriſt, the righteouſneſſe which is of God by faith, Phil. 3 9.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Sort are all thoſe formall profeſſors, who ſeem onely to be religious. Iames 1.26. <hi>Having a forme of Godlineſſe, but denying the power thereof.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.5. Theſe will tell you they reſt not on duties, truſt not to their owne righteauſneſſe, confide not in their Humiliation, as legal pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors doe; But they (after much trouble of conſcience for their ſins) got comfort, joy, and peace in applying ſome promiſes of the Goſpell to themſelves: Conſider, I pray you, the Parable of the ſtony ground hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers. They on the rock, are they, which when thy hear receive the Word with joy, and theſe have no root, which for a while beleeve, and in time of temptation fall away, Luke 8.13. Here was ſome (plowing, though it went not deep enough,) and ſome Harrowing alſo, to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the good ſeed; after this the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was ſome joy, but no root; Here was
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:158497:11"/>the Word convincing, and wounding, and comforting, but no Chriſt (who is called the root Coloſſ. 2.6, 7) to quicken, renew, and ſanctifie: And therefore, though they believed awhile, yet they fall away, in the time of Temptation. And this is the condition of formall Profeſſors, they get comfort in promiſes, but they receive not Chriſt and His ſanctifying comforting-ſpirit in the promiſes, let ſuch hear what the Lord by His Prophet ſpeakes to a formall profeſsing people, Iſa. 50.11. <hi>Behold, all ye that kindle a fire, that compaſſe your ſelves about with ſparks; Walk in the light of your fire, and in the ſparks that ye have kindled. This ſhall ye have at my hand, ye ſhall lye down in ſorrow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third ſort are all thoſe carnall Profeſſors, who ſay they are the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, and hold the common Faith, Titus 1.4. which is the faith of Gods Elect, Titus 1.1. and beleeve the common ſalvation: Jude 3. That is to ſay, common to every one that beleeveth, both Jew and Gentile: Rom. 1, 16. But notwithſtanding all this profeſſion of generall redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption: 2 Pet. 2.19. For they take liberty to live in ſin, and walk after the fleſh fulfilling the luſts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; turning the grace of God into laſciviouſneſſe, and denying the onely Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Jude 4 They are ſo fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re departed from the Faith, which they ſometime profeſſed, and ſeemed to have, 1 Tim. 4.1. that they queſtion whether the Scriptures of truth be the Word of God? Whether Chriſt be the ſonne of God? Whether the firſt day of the Week be the Sabboth of God? And they are ſo farre from li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving godly, and walking in the way of holineſſe; that they totally omit all holy duties, they refrain prayer, they ſpeak not of the Word of God when they riſe up, nor when they lye down, nor as they ſin in the houſe together with their family: They do not pertake of any Ordinances, nor perform any worſhip to God. And as for ſin, they make a mock at it; ſome of them ſay God takes no knowledge of their ſins, He ſees no iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in them; others affirm, that they have no ſin, they are born of God, and they cannot ſin: And ſome others are bold, to ſay, they are juſtified perſons, and therfore all their words and actions are alike acceptable to God, and well-pleaſing in his ſight &amp;c. But theſe carnall profeſſors are not holy, are not the people of God: This may make ſome diſcovery of thoſe, whoſe hearts are not right with God; to whom I would give the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles exhortation, Acts 8.22.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Vſe.</hi> Will God have His people to be holy? Then may this doctrine occaſion a deep Humiliation, and godly ſorrow in believers for their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holineſſe, carnallneſſe, and ſinfulneſſe in heart or life, O beloved, let you and I commune with our own hearts, how much unbelief, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie, ſelf-filthineſſe, formality and wickedneſſe, ſhall we upon diligent examination finde ſtill remaining in us? What vanity of minde and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nality is in our hearts? How many hard thoughts of God have we ſtill?
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:158497:11"/>Notwithſtanding all the experiences God hath given us of his unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe, his faithfulneſſe, and his everlaſting loving kindneſſe in Jeſus Chriſt: How apt are we by an evill heart of unbelief, to depart from God? Alas what ſinfull contemplations have we in our ſpirits? What evill concupiſcence? How do our hearts run out after the creature-com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of this world, and how are our affections ſtill ſet upon the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt and God? How many Idols are ſet up in our hearts! How great is our ſelf-love, ſelf-ſeeking, ſelf-confidence, ſelf-dependence, and ſelf-ſufficiencie! O what high thoughts have we ſometimes of our ſelves, our gifts, our graces, our experiences, our performances? Surely we have juſt cauſe (if God will in mercy work in us godly ſorrow) to be aſhamed, to mourn after a godly manner, and to loath our ſelves for the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of our own hearts. But my brethren, let us examine our lives, and ſearch and try our wayes, as well as commune with our hearts, for the eye of the world is open upon us; God, and Angels, men and Divels, all obſerve us (who are believers) they hear what we ſay, and take know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge what we do. O beloved, how much vain, carnall, and ſinfull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication comes out of our mouthes, that miniſters no grace to the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers! How many idle words do we ſpeak? What unprofitable talk have we among our ſelves and with others; not gracious, nor ſeaſoned with the ſalt of truth and holineſſe, but very unſavoury ſpeeches. And when we meet together, and ſpeak one to another of Religion, we are apt to ſpeak ſlightly, raſhly, formally, inconſiderately, and not ſoberly, humbly, and graciouſly, as becomes the Saints. Yea, our conferences ſometimes turns to vain janglings, and un-edifying diſputes, wherein we ſtrive for victory, or to maintain our own opinion, more then truth; But beſides all this, How much ungodlineſſe is there in our actions? Albeit God preventeth us by His grace, from doing actions ſimply and groſſely evill and ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as drunkenneſſe, uncleanneſſe, &amp;c. Yet in doing lawfull things, we often miſ-carry; the Meſſengers of Chriſt do ſometimes preach them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, Fathers of Families do correct their children ſometimes after their pleaſure, provoking their children, being bitter to their Wives ſometimes; Oh how uneven do we walk in our callings and relations! Wherein we ſhould eſpecially ſhew forth the power of godlineſſe. Oh had we tender hearts and were we truly ſenſible of our ſinfull miſcariages, we could not ſpeak of thoſe particulars without teares of godly ſorrow. Can we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how many yeares we have profeſſed the Goſpell, how long we have enjoyed the Word preached in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon unto us, and yet how little our converſation is as becomes the Goſpell, how little we have profited, how little we have grown in Grace, and in the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, and not be affected to mourn under the feeling of our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitableneſſe, and great barrenneſſe. But I hope God will give us re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:158497:12"/>unto ſalvation, not to be repented of for all our unrighteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Vſe.</hi> Will God have his people to be holy? Let it be uſefull for the conſolation of every true Believer, eſpecially ſuch as at preſent groane under the tyrannicall power, or captivating bondage of any corruption; And ſigh to God for ſupply from Chriſt of any grace wanting, or weake in their apprehenſion, ſenſe, and feeling. Hearken poor mourning ſoul, and conſider what may be ſaid for thy comfort, and ſearch the Scriptures whether it be ſo or not.</p>
            <p>Know firſt, That Gods eternall purpoſe toward thee (who art a true Beleever) in chuſing thee in Chriſt, was, that thou ſhouldeſt be holy, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſ. 1.4 and Rom. 8.30. I have purpoſed it (ſaith God) I will alſo do it, Iſa. 46.11.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That God hath made with thee an everlaſting Covenant of Grace and Holineſſe, wherein he hath given thee many great and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes, to pardon ſin, to ſubdue iniquity, and to put his Law in thy minde, and write it in thy heart: Jer. 3.31.34, and 32.40, with Heb. 8.10.11.12. Micah. 7.18, 19, 20, with 2 Pet. 2.3, 4, to the 11. verſ.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that Chriſt hath prayed to His Father for thee, that he would ſanctifie thee, John 17.1.17.20.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, that Chriſt ſanctified himſelf for thy ſake, that thou alſo might be ſanctified, Joh. 17.19.20.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, that God hath given thee the ſpirit of his ſonne, Gal. 4.6. who is a comforting ſanctifying ſpirit, yea the Comforter; John 14.16, 17.18: And he that ſanctifieth all the people of God, 1 Theſ. 5.23.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, That faithfull is God, who called thee, who alſo will do it; 1 Theſ. 5.24. He called thee unto Holineſſe, 1 Theſ 4.7, and he will both make thee holy. [He hath ſaid thou ſhalt be holy, Levit. 11.44.45, and 19.2. That is ſuch a command, as hath the force of a promiſe in it; And though that place, Levit. 20 7, is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie your ſelves therefore and be ye Holy;</hi> yet the 70. Interpreters renders it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Et ſanctificabimi, &amp; eritis ſancti.</hi> And ſo doth the Chaldees Paraphraſt render it alſo. And <hi>Hierom</hi> tranſlates that place, in the firſt of Pet. 1.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Be ye holy, <hi>Sancti eritis,</hi> Ye ſhall be holy: And indeed, there is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the Margent of one Greek Teſtament, for God can put a being to His Word] And therefore be of good comfort, thy ſinnes are forgiven thee. Matth. 9.2. And ſinne ſhall not have dominion over thee, Rom. 6.14. The grace of Chriſt is ſufficient for thee, 2 Cor. 12.9. He is full of grace, John 1.14. And from his ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, thou ſhalt receive grace upon grace; John 1.16. According as his divine power hath given us all things, that pertain unto life and godlineſſe. 1. Pet. 1.3.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Vſe.</hi> Will God have his people to be holy? Let me conclude with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:158497:12"/>an uſe of exhortation to holineſſe; <hi>As he that called you is holy, ſo be ye holy in all manner of Converſation,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. God will have his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple holy at all times, in all relations, and in every condition. Therefore I beſeech you brethren, and exhort you in the Lord, and for his ſake, to be holy in all manner of Converſation, holy in your callings, for godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is great gaine: holy in your Families, in your ſhops, in your jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyes in all your waies, and in all your relations. Godlineſſe hath the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe both of this life, &amp; that which is to come. Piety hath a majeſtie in it, it will give you a throne in the Conſciences of others, that they dare not ſin in your preſence. Holineſſe is an ornament to your callings, to your perſons, to your families, and to the place where you live. The more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the more like your Heavenly Father, and the more you, glorifie your heavenly Father, and the more you adorne the Doctrine of Chriſt, yea the more communion you have with the Father and with Chriſt. Having therefore theſe promiſes, dearly beloved, let us cleanſe our ſelves from all filthineſſe of the fleſh and ſpirit, perfecting ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in the feare of God, 2 Cor. 7.1, 4. great is my boldneſſe of ſpeech toward you in this exhortation, becauſe I deſire fruit that may abound to your account; And give me leave to preſſe this exhortation upon ſuch beleevers preſent who have carnall parents, yoke-fellowes, or other car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall friends. You would have your naturall friends converted, and to that end you pray for them, mourne over them, many a ſigh, and many a tear, it may be, they have coſt you; but they live in the fleſh ſtill, are carnall ſtill. Oh let not an holy converſation be wanting, that may further their converſion, 1 Cor. 7.16, 17. And if any obey not the Word, they alſo may be wonne, without the word, by your Godly converſation, 1 Pet. 3.1. And if they be not drawn thereby to a love of the truth, yet their mouthes will be ſtopped, that they cannot ſpeake againſt it. Would it not be a comfortable thing, to have a carnall father ſpeake thus of his godly ſon, or daughter, to wit, I was unwilling my children ſhould go ſo often to heare Sermons, and be ſo often at Conferences, and private faſts, and the like; But I have obſerved, that ſince they profeſſed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and gave themſelves to pray, and read the Scriptures, They have been much more dutifull to us their parents then before, and they are more diligent in their callings. If this be the worſt, they ſhall have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to profeſſe the Goſpell ſtill. The like I might ſpeak of other relations but ſhould carnall parents or friends have cauſe by your looſe or un even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>walking to ſpeak evill of the waies of God, it would bee very uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable to you, and diſhonourable to the Goſpell. I ſhall conclude in the words of the Apoſtle, Phil. 4.8. Finally, Brethren, Whatſoever things are true, Whatſoever things are honeſt, juſt, pure, lovely, or of good report. If there be any vertue, and if there be any praiſe, thinke on theſe things, and the God of peace ſhall be with you. verſ. 9.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:158497:13"/>
            <p>One objection had need to be anſwered, before I end, and that is this; May ſome ſay, you have exhorted us to holineſſe, and the Apoſtle tells us, 2 Tim. 3.12. All that will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, ſhall ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> How may wee be encouraged and ſtrengthened againſt the feares of perſecution?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solu.</hi> I anſwer, Firſt pray to God, that he will furniſh you with ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring graces, againſt perſecuting times, Coloſ. 1.9.10, 11. Secondly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove your intereſt through Chriſt in the promiſes, and beleeve, that the more ſufferings for Chriſt, the more comfort by Chriſt, 2 Cor. 1.5. The more ſufferings the more holineſſe, Heb. 12.10. The more ſufferings the more happineſſe: 1 Pet. 4.14. Onely take heed of ſuffering as an evill doer, verſes 15.16. And if any ſuffer as a Chriſtian, Chriſt will ſuffer with him, Iſa. 63.9. Chriſt will ſhare with you in your ſuffering perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution. Acts 9.4, 5. And you ſhall ſhare with Chriſt in glory, Rom. 8.17. But you muſt bee holy in ſufferings alſo, praying for them that perſecute you, as Chriſt taught and practiſed: and ſo did his Martyr <hi>Stephen,</hi> 7.60. <hi>Lord lay not this ſin to their charge:</hi> And ſo let us pray for them that now diſturbed us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
